<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>cyberlingual - musings</title><link href="https://megankarabin.github.io/cyberlingual/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://megankarabin.github.io/cyberlingual/feeds/musings.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://megankarabin.github.io/cyberlingual/</id><updated>2021-05-07T20:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Thought parsing: Information, communication, and intelligence</title><link href="https://megankarabin.github.io/cyberlingual/musings-i.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-07T20:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-05-07T20:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Megan Karabin</name></author><id>tag:megankarabin.github.io,2021-05-07:/cyberlingual/musings-i.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h5&gt;is information just an attributional property of the interaction between space-time (non-exclusive to matter, but rather anything that exists&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;) and&amp;nbsp;perception?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matter (within the bounds and constraints of space-time in the observable universe) and space itself has certain qualitative attributes&amp;mdash;in the form of physical properties, broadly speaking&amp;mdash;like …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h5&gt;is information just an attributional property of the interaction between space-time (non-exclusive to matter, but rather anything that exists&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;) and&amp;nbsp;perception?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matter (within the bounds and constraints of space-time in the observable universe) and space itself has certain qualitative attributes&amp;mdash;in the form of physical properties, broadly speaking&amp;mdash;like mass, energy, and density (on the elemental side), and colour, texture/surface variation, and the like (on the secondary, or emergent-property side). The vacuum of space is, well, a vacuum. It contains no substance, has no atmosphere&amp;mdash;in other words, there is an absence of matter. Science notably uses these qualities&amp;mdash;this &lt;em&gt;information&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;to draw conclusions about things (e.g., their past, present and future states), and the relationship between such things and other things. I would argue that the term “information” is in many ways analogous to the question of whether a tree makes a sound when it falls but no one is around to hear it. Quantum theories, of course, would say that the tree neither fell nor didn’t until the moment an observer happened upon it, and in perceiving it, forced an outcome. Information is much the same—consider the observer effect. Information&amp;mdash;e.g., photon behaviour&amp;mdash;can be altered &lt;em&gt;depending on whether it is being measured or not&lt;/em&gt;. This brings us back to the original suggestion: that information is only possibly conceived as such if there is in fact an “informee”, an observer or perceiving entity, to be informed. One might counter that we could have information but be unable to make use of it, such as if one received a letter written in a foreign language, with an altogether unfamiliar orthography. While it is true that you might not be able to understand the intended semantic content (if indeed there was any to begin with—but let’s assume that this letter was written by a real person, in their—real—native language, so there was), you are still able to access the informational output (the symbols), only you don’t have the key to hash the author’s meaning. On the other hand, we could consider information to simply be anything that is, and specifically, anything that can either be measured or observed, or be inferred based on other measurements and observations. Information is…stuff. Or patterns caused by stuff. Which itself, is effectively stuff (though perhaps qualitatively different stuff, via a human understanding). While this definition doesn’t explicitly necessitate the existence of a perceiver, it is implicitly&amp;nbsp;commanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Language as a basis for communication of&amp;nbsp;information&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tend to think that language represents an objective reality, at least to some degree, because functionally, it would appear that way. You can input an address into a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; and arrive at your destination flawlessly (in theory) solely by following verbal directions provided by the disembodied robot-woman voice projecting from the device. Proof&amp;mdash;language reflects objective reality. It, like so many other examples of exquisite cooperation and task execution made possible exclusively by language, is compelling evidence that language does consistently transmit information effectively and successfully. Yet there are infinite things that we do not have words for. Language, therefore, reflects but a tiny sliver of That Which Exists, and in order to better understand ourselves&amp;mdash;human cognition, reasoning, learning&amp;mdash;we must ask: what pieces, which parts of perceivable reality do we attend to, such that they achieve lexicalized status in our collective vocabulary? Which concepts, which forms, which configurations of matter—and which relationships between forms and configurations—are salient to humans such that we linguistically (and by extension conceptually) materialize their existence? Of course the answer is right in front of us: those which &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; linguistically materialized, as lexical-semantic entries. And so, we might approach this from a slightly different angle: given the linguistic-conceptual distribution observed (cross-linguistically&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, as well) what are the features of reality that human beings attend to? More abstractly, how do humans attend to, identify, classify and categorize, and prioritize &lt;em&gt;information&lt;/em&gt; available from their environment (not necessarily in the order listed), and specifically, do so in order to acquire and use language, and then further use the language they have to acquire new, often more complex information and concepts? Are the processes (i.e., the initial learning involved in language acquisition and the learning facilitated by language literacy) analogous? On a slightly divergent note, there is a wealth of literature and previous work on language concreteness, which distinguishes between concrete and abstract language, and significant evidence supports a differentiation between the two (child acquisition, comprehension/processing, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LCM&lt;/span&gt;). However, a “chair”, despite representing a concrete thing (as opposed to, say, “justice”, a markedly abstract label in terms of what it represents), is unavoidably abstract&amp;mdash;it is arbitrary (no correspondence in features between the label and the thing it represents, cf. de Saussure), and also requires that we have a stored conceptual prototype for that which constitutes a chair. How do we differentiate a chair from a table? From a stool? From a short bench? Broadly speaking, the answer is by their&amp;mdash;&lt;em&gt;differential&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;salient features. But let us pause, and consider: what does “salient” actually mean here? Salience in this context&amp;mdash;as in most&amp;mdash;refers to &lt;em&gt;perceptual&lt;/em&gt; salience. Perceptual salience presupposes a perceiver&amp;mdash;and naturally, we, humans, are the perceivers (of course we could include other animals under this umbrella without altering the argument in any significant way). So, more precisely, the answer to the question of how we differentiate (e.g. functionally similar) objects is actually: by their perceptually salient differential/distinguishing features. The problem of artificial intelligence (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;) primitiveness, in many ways, is linked to this (largely) defining property of general intelligence (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GI&lt;/span&gt;) and categorization ability in humans. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; is capable of far surpassing human computational and predictive ability in many respects, and capable of modeling data (extracting patterns from and organizing information) in ways a human being is simply not able to do. Yet humans still outperform &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; on nearly every domain-general skill and especially, famously, natural language use. In perceiving, humans are critically, selectively and preferentially attending to certain specific patterns and pieces of information that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; algorithms are not. Is this because they (the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;) are attending equally to all information? Or selectively attending to different pieces of information? Or, selectively attending to the same information, but in a qualitatively&amp;mdash;even categorically&amp;mdash;different way? Or, is it because an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; algorithm is only exposed to a slice of data, compared to the virtually infinite information&amp;mdash;and potential loci of focus—available to humans from the moment of birth onward through their existence? To be precise, it isn’t the information per se that is infinite, but rather, the possibilities arising from innumerable potential interpretations of it, in countless different conceptualizations. And so equally interesting, is it not, that despite this overwhelming quantity of data, of sensory stimuli that we must constantly, ceaselessly sift through and process, that we collectively settle on very consistent interpretations. This would appear to be a function less of the inherent salience of any particular feature or facet of information, and more one of the human condition. This epistemological, Kantian quandary poses a unique problem for the puzzle of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;, with a twist: if we can only know the world and reality such as we subjectively perceive it via our senses (and by extension our cognition), how can we expect an artificial (i.e., not naturally occurring, as in biological life-forms created via sexual reproduction) intelligence to perform complex, human-centric tasks (some of which, like language, as well as music, are fundamental and universal in our species) with a high degree of efficacy unless it is imbued with the same motivations, capacities, and tools as those of humans which are required to carry out such functions? Additionally, the problem of stunted artificial intelligence invites us, in a rather meta way, to revisit the concept-label mapping of the term “artificial intelligence” itself, along with its corresponding conceptual realization. It’s interesting that the bar for what is considered intelligence artificially is apparently much lower than the criteria for evaluation of natural intelligence. This discordance may lie at the heart of the issues faced by the field, and may also be the key to novel breakthroughs and discovery. Perhaps through no ill intent, the term &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt; has been misappropriated in an excited haste to christen a but-nascent field with a title it has not earned. Intelligence must be globally operationalized (i.e., defined) if we are to make greater strides toward machine learning algorithms that can competently carry out complex tasks at a human-like (or human-superior) level of ability&amp;mdash;including learning and generalizing knowledge. This last point raises the additional and nontrivial concern of whether or not we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; strive to create a system with human-based intelligence, and thus demands rigorous, careful, and holistic ethical consideration before proceeding with active attempts to create such an&amp;nbsp;entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;in this discussion, “exists” is simply a convenient/simplified way of saying “anything measurable within the bounds and constraints of the physics of the observable universe” (including emergent properties and relationships between&amp;nbsp;things)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;this would additionally require a typological investigation/comparison to see if there are any differences in this distribution as a function of language or language family, but assuming for now that the distribution is similar&amp;nbsp;cross-linguistically&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="musings"></category></entry><entry><title>Everything is language</title><link href="https://megankarabin.github.io/cyberlingual/everything-is-language.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Megan Karabin</name></author><id>tag:megankarabin.github.io,2021-02-12:/cyberlingual/everything-is-language.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mathematical notation: language. Stock market and finance jargon: language. Poetry:&amp;nbsp;language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last one is obvious, but you may not have thought about math and stocks as being fundamentally linguistic. The language (i.e., words) used can still &amp;#8220;correspond&amp;#8221; to English&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;mdash;or whatever your native language may be&amp;mdash;but …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mathematical notation: language. Stock market and finance jargon: language. Poetry:&amp;nbsp;language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last one is obvious, but you may not have thought about math and stocks as being fundamentally linguistic. The language (i.e., words) used can still &amp;#8220;correspond&amp;#8221; to English&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;mdash;or whatever your native language may be&amp;mdash;but it isn&amp;#8217;t always easily understood, and can feel quite foreign, if we&amp;#8217;re not familiar with the subject. This is a perfect example of context-dependent language, where, in North America, for example, the English you speak at home with your family is likely very different from the English you hear on a trading floor (unless you&amp;#8217;re from a family of bankers, maybe). Go into a software company&amp;#8217;s innovation or R&amp;amp;D department, or an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt; branch of a cybersecurity company, or sit in on a symphony orchestra practicing, a gender studies class, or a court hearing or legal briefing. Listen to the language used at a university football practice, on a construction site, in a professional kitchen. What differentiates each of these domains? Of course the things they deal with seem vastly different&amp;mdash;sports, music, law, design, economics, philosophy and critical thought, computer programming&amp;mdash;but yet, any child who speaks the English language could grow up to participate in any one&amp;mdash;or any number&amp;mdash;of these fields. The common denominator is English. Yet&amp;mdash;what might you notice, in each of these environments? Would you be able to jump into the conversation in each of these places? Perhaps it would be the case that, given a lack of background knowledge or experience, you might find you are actually able to understand very little of what is being said. Is this because you&amp;#8217;re not intelligent enough, or don&amp;#8217;t have a handle on the English language? Of course not. Too often people&amp;mdash;capable, intelligent, valuable people&amp;mdash;are driven away from a domain because they feel unequipped to join the conversation. They assume that because they don&amp;#8217;t understand what&amp;#8217;s being said&amp;mdash;often in their own native language, no less&amp;mdash;they are either ill-suited to this particular subject matter, or they simply are not capable enough. This is &amp;#8220;starting at the end&amp;#8221;, as it were. Let&amp;#8217;s suppose you heard Zulu being spoken, and thought to yourself, &amp;#8220;what a beautiful language&amp;#8221;. Interested in learning it, you decided to sit in on an advanced Zulu class, and found that you understood nothing. Would you&amp;mdash;a beginner, with no prior knowledge of the language&amp;mdash;abandon the idea of pursuing learning Zulu altogether because you didn&amp;#8217;t understand what was being discussed at a predictably challenging higher level? Or, perhaps more interestingly, would you have even expected yourself to understand what was&amp;nbsp;happening?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a sense that in learning a new language, one must start at the beginning. You need to first build up a vocabulary, an understanding of the structure of the language, knowledge about the culture in which the language is&amp;nbsp;spoken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The same principle applies to every conceptual domain one can think of&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There should be no shame in the naive quality of being a newcomer to a topic. Additionally, there should be no fear of a subject simply because at first pass, you find you&amp;#8217;re not quite able to understand or repeat back the new information. To the former: being a newcomer means you are unfamiliar with the jargon. It&amp;#8217;s as simple as that. It doesn&amp;#8217;t mean you&amp;#8217;re unable to grasp the information, the meaning, hidden being the terminology, but rather that you haven&amp;#8217;t yet learned what that&amp;mdash;often specific, often domain-specific&amp;mdash;meaning is. Take the term &lt;em&gt;polysemous&lt;/em&gt;. A perfect word for this context. As a linguist, I need to take care not to scare non-linguists away by using *unusual* terms (especially where I could choose more general, or domain-common, words instead). Notice I won&amp;#8217;t say &amp;#8220;big&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;complex&amp;#8221; words&amp;mdash;because other (small and simple yet equally confounding) words could fit here too. In any case, it&amp;#8217;s about relating to people. So rather than say domain-specific words can be confusing because they&amp;#8217;re often polysemous, I might say they can be confusing because they often have more than one meaning. Polysemous = has more than one meaning. Easy,&amp;nbsp;right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;poly&lt;/em&gt; =&amp;nbsp;many&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;
&lt;em&gt;sem&lt;/em&gt; = sign&amp;nbsp;(Greek)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;
&lt;em&gt;-ous&lt;/em&gt; = adjective&amp;nbsp;suffix&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(suffix = thing you add onto the end of a word to make a new word.)
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason that domain-specific words (and often, colloquially, &amp;#8220;big&amp;#8221; words) (yes, I used a five-syllable word in an aside about big words. I can&amp;#8217;t help myself. It means &amp;#8220;informal&amp;#8221;, sort of synonymous with &amp;#8220;the vernacular&amp;#8221;) seem scary is because they&amp;#8217;re &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt;! They look and sound like our language, yet we don&amp;#8217;t have any meaning to assign them. It&amp;#8217;s like having a label that doesn&amp;#8217;t refer to anything. Imagine someone kept talking about &amp;#8220;Anna&amp;#8221;, but you didn&amp;#8217;t know who Anna was, anything about her life, or what she did, or what she looked like. You wouldn&amp;#8217;t really have much to contribute to the discussion about Anna per se&amp;mdash;but you might ask those things as questions.  It&amp;#8217;s like when you go to a new restaurant with dishes you&amp;#8217;ve never heard of or tried before on the menu. Sometimes all it takes is a peek behind the curtain, so to speak, to get a sense of what  kind of food the label refers to. It is fairly intuitive that when you go to, say, a Mexican restaurant, you might learn that &amp;#8220;pollo&amp;#8221; means chicken. If you only spoke English going into the restaurant, now you have two entries&amp;mdash;i.e., labels, i.e., {&amp;#8220;chicken&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;pollo&amp;#8221;}&amp;mdash;in your mind for the food-concept that is chicken. What about the other way around? What does the word chicken &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt;? That is, what concept does the entry &amp;#8220;chicken&amp;#8221; correspond to? Does it only have one meaning? Let&amp;#8217;s think about this. If you were reading a children&amp;#8217;s book about a farm, what does &amp;#8220;chicken&amp;#8221; evoke? What about at a restaurant? What about with your friends before a swim in the lake on a cold morning? Though we might be unaware of it, we already have many words in our lexicon&amp;mdash;our &amp;#8220;mental dictionary&amp;#8221;&amp;mdash;that have multiple different meanings. Same label, different stuff. How and when we use these words, and each of their meanings, depends largely (if not entirely) on the context. Now think back to each of the places and domains I talked about at the beginning&amp;mdash;not only do different domains have different &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; words, they also have words that look and sound familiar, but carry an either somewhat or entirely different&amp;nbsp;meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to conclude, for now, this yet unfinished thought: one mustn&amp;#8217;t fear. Just remember everything is language and you&amp;#8217;ll be&amp;nbsp;fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; the example language for the current purposes, both for simplification (i.e., to avoid having to say &amp;#8220;language&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;any language&amp;#8221; at every turn) and to make clear that this &amp;#8220;language&amp;#8221; of which I wish to speak (at least where you now see &amp;#8220;English&amp;#8221; in the above text) unambiguously points to [a] human natural language, and not language as in phrasing or stylistic considerations or verbiage. All that to say, one could easily insert any other natural language (e.g., Hungarian, Inuktitut, Japanese, Pirahã) and the same principle holds. (The question of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; this is is subject matter for another story time&amp;#8230;)
 O blessed footnote, how unironically recursive thou&amp;nbsp;art&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="musings"></category></entry><entry><title>A brief reflection on language and cultural norms + values</title><link href="https://megankarabin.github.io/cyberlingual/language-culture.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Megan Karabin</name></author><id>tag:megankarabin.github.io,2021-02-05:/cyberlingual/language-culture.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is interesting how much of our language is shaped by cultural mores and social institutions. &amp;#8220;Social institutions&amp;#8221; though, are of course made up of individuals, who each and together hold cultural values and personal&amp;nbsp;biases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The now-productive English prefix &lt;em&gt;andro-&lt;/em&gt; was borrowed from the Greek &lt;em&gt;andr-&lt;/em&gt; meaning &amp;#8220;man&amp;#8221; or …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is interesting how much of our language is shaped by cultural mores and social institutions. &amp;#8220;Social institutions&amp;#8221; though, are of course made up of individuals, who each and together hold cultural values and personal&amp;nbsp;biases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The now-productive English prefix &lt;em&gt;andro-&lt;/em&gt; was borrowed from the Greek &lt;em&gt;andr-&lt;/em&gt; meaning &amp;#8220;man&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;male&amp;#8221;. We see this form all over&amp;mdash;from android (literally, &amp;#8220;man-like&amp;#8221;) to andragogy (the study of adult learning; contrasted with pedagogy&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;) to androgen (the so-called &amp;#8220;male&amp;#8221; sex hormone&amp;mdash;so-called in that people of both sexes produce and require androgens, just as people of both sexes produce and require estrogen). The feminine counterpart to &lt;em&gt;andr-&lt;/em&gt;, in Greek, is &lt;em&gt;gune-&lt;/em&gt;, whose English form is recognizable as &lt;em&gt;gynaeco-&lt;/em&gt;, defined as &amp;#8220;relating to women;&amp;nbsp;female&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- {Looking at these combining forms in corpora - how does the productivity (derivational family; proportion of new/obscure uses) of each compare?} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s interesting how German educator &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Kapp_(German_educator_and_editor)"&gt;Alexander Kapp&lt;/a&gt; (1799-1869), in creating a new term for his philosophy of adult education (andragogy), chose to use the Greek form for man (and it doesn&amp;#8217;t mean &amp;#8220;man&amp;#8221; as in the dated synonym for &amp;#8220;human&amp;#8221;, it relates specifically to a &amp;#8220;masculine&amp;#8221;, or male, quality)&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. Developed in the first half of the 19th century, it is easy to see why this choice made sense, at the time. A reflection, indeed, of the fact that at that time, women were excluded from most of higher education (among other domains). But interesting, still, that the etymology of the term gives us hints as to the cultural state of affairs at its&amp;nbsp;inception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the increasing prevalence of women&amp;#8217;s participation in society in all spheres, at all levels, language use has adapted: much more frequent are the more accurate &amp;#8220;humankind&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;salesperson&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;chair of the board&amp;#8221;. The question of causation vs. correlation aside, this is rather&amp;nbsp;cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also interesting is how &lt;em&gt;gynaeco-&lt;/em&gt; in its widest-used combined form is gynecology, the branch of medicine dealing with women&amp;#8217;s reproductive health. Of note on a personal level: I was already comfortably familiar with &lt;em&gt;andro-&lt;/em&gt; as the combining form for &amp;#8220;man/male&amp;#8221;, but until closer inspection had assumed &lt;em&gt;gynaeco&lt;/em&gt; referred to some aspect of the female reproductive system, rather than simply being the counterpart, if you will, of &lt;em&gt;andro-&lt;/em&gt;. If andragogy and its roots give us any clues, we might consider looking at gynecology through a similar lens. Why is it that this term has as its literal meaning (constructed by combining its constituent parts, &lt;em&gt;gynaeco-&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;ology&lt;/em&gt;) &amp;#8220;the study of women&amp;#8221;, but this medical discipline is focused on the reproductive system? Of course, there is also andrology, which deals with conditions and diseases specific to men. However, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the case that the medical model itself&amp;mdash; at the level of the institution, not just the discipline&amp;mdash;is biased toward the male body as the standard, or the baseline, and the female body as a variation, as such&amp;mdash;a proportionately smaller version of the standard. While this is very much not the case, it doesn&amp;#8217;t change the fact that, for example, car manufacturers still use anatomically male crash dummies, and women are at a greater risk of serious injury and death because seatbelts haven&amp;#8217;t been tested on female-proportioned dummy-subjects&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, a question that arises is: how might the differential usage of such terms reflect conceptual filaments, or substrates, within a culture or a society? How might an androcentric lens (largely the result of few alternate and equally influential perspectives in academic and social disciplines) have shaped some of this vocabulary, and what does it mean for us now? From words (&amp;#8220;hysteria&amp;#8221;) to idioms (&amp;#8220;grow a pair/have the balls&amp;#8221;), the language we use is directly influenced by culture&amp;mdash;whether aligned with current norms and values or vestigal clues to past&amp;nbsp;worldviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;meaning is not the sum of its&amp;nbsp;parts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; pedagogy is the more general term, referring to &amp;#8220;the method and practice of teaching&amp;#8221; (cited from Merriam-Webster English dictionary). Andragogy is essentially similar, but specifies teaching in the context of adult&amp;nbsp;learners.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; A fairly random and context-less example; I came across this figure+term while reading an article about communication, and it spurred these thoughts. Will try to find it again and link it&amp;nbsp;here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.ca/Invisible-Women-Data-World-Designed/dp/1419735217/ref=sr_1_1?dchild=1&amp;amp;keywords=invisible+women&amp;amp;qid=1621038394&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;Caroline Criado Perez, Invisible Women&amp;nbsp;(2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="musings"></category></entry></feed>